Guide to the Brian Gilmore papers, 1977-2014 MS2257
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brian Gilmore papers
1977-2014
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2257
4 Linear Feet
This collection containes poems, essays, articles, notebooks, correspondence, fliers, clippings and other materials relating to the literary works of Washington D.C. poet Brian Gilmore. Included are articles from publications including the Washington Post, Detriot Free Press, the Washington Afro American, DC North, the Houston Chronicle and the Progressive as well as research files collected while composing these pieces. Topics include Malcolm X, Duke Ellington, the death penalty, gradutaion rates of athletes, voting rights and critiques of government policies. The material dates from 1977-2014.
Biographical / Historical
Brian Gilmore, is a poet and writer living in the District of Columbia and Lansing Michigan. His first collection of poetry, "elvis presley is alive and well and living in harlem" was published by THIRD WORLD PRESS of Chicago in 1993. His poetry has appeared in numerous anthologies and he has taught poetry at the Catholic University of America and at Lorton Prison. Brian has published essays in The Nation, The Washington City Paper, The Washington Afro-American, and in "Soulfires: Black Men on Love and Violence". His fiction has been published in Obsidian II and Gargoyle while his book reviews have been widely published in many national publications. He has written for the Christian Science Monitor, The Washington Post, Emerge Magazine, and Africana.com. He has lectured at the Associated Writing Programs Annual Conference (1996 and 1997), Emory University in Atlanta, and has appeared on National Public Radio's "This American Life".
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Brian Gilmore, 2008 (2008.057) and 2011 (2011.032); 2013 (2013.001) and 2014 (2014.024)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into 5 series: Writings by Brian Gilmore, Writings by other authors, Research materials, Publicity, and Personal files.
Scope and Contents
This collection containes articles, essays, poetry, research material, correspondence and other materials relating to the works of Washington D.C. poet Brian Gilmore. The material dates from 1977-2014.
Contained within the collection are the multifaceted opinions and views of Brian Gilmore communicated through different types of written media. Poetry, editorials, reviews, articles, essays, and scripts cover topics as diverse as Duke Ellington, capital punishment University basketball, Government reform, Washington D.C. home rule, street violence, poverty, civil rights, and music. The research files allow a researcher the rare chance to view the exact materials that the artist has pulled from in the creation process. The notebooks and unfinished poems provide the opportunity to watch the maturing and editing to which a writer must subject thier work.
Civil rights; African Americans; Washington (D.C.) -- History; Music -- Washington (D.C.); Poetry -- African American poets; Home rule; Politics and government; Gilmore, Brian
- Writings by Brian Gilmore, 1988-2012; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: Original donations and Accession from 2014. This arrangement was chosen because the accretion from 2014 could not easily be added to the existing arrangment for this series. Therefore two series were created to maintain the order of the first series, but allow for an understandable arrangement for the second series.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains poems, articles and essays written by Brian Gilmore. The material dates from 1988-2012.
  - Original donations, Series 1 Subseries 1
    Original donation arranged alphabetically by title of work. Accessions that follow the original donation will be organized in accordance with original order and will most likely adhere to the article / poetry split, but will not be interfiled by title aphabetically with the existing collection.
    This subseries contains poems, articles and essays written by Brian Gilmore. The material dates from 1988-2012.
    - Articles: A-G, 2001-2007; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Articles: A-G, 1999-2010; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Articles: A-G, 1999-2010; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Articles: H-O, 1998-2008; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Articles: H-O, 1999-2010; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Articles: P-Z, 1988-2007; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Articles: P-Z, 1999-2010; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Articles: P-Z, 1999-2010; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Articles [accession 2012], 2002-2012; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Essays: A-G, 1988-1996; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Essays: I-Z, 1988-1996; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Essays: Untitled, Undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Poetry: A-C, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Poetry: D-G, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Poetry: H-K, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Poetry: L-M, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Poetry: S-T, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Poetry: N-R, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Poetry: U-Z, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Poetry collections: Jungle Nights and Soda Fountain Rags, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      General
      Bound copy
    - Poetry: without titles, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Scripts, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Works in progress, undated; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Poetry collections, 1997-1999; Series 1 Subseries 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Containes the Bridge, volume 1 no. 1 and issue 2, the Drumming volumes 3, 4 and 5 and the Redbrick Review.
  - Accession from 2014, 1990-2014; Series 1 Subseries 2
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of Brian Gilmore, July 14, 2014 (2014.024)
    Arranged loosely alphabetical.
    - Articles [originally foldered together], 1990-2004; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Articles, Circa 2000 - Circa 2010; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Articles, Circa 2001 - Circa 2010; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Articles, Circa 2000 - Circa 2010; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Articles, Circa 2000 - Circa 2010; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Articles, Circa 2001 - Circa 2010; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Articles in magazines, 1999-2003; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Articles in magazines, 2003-2012; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper articles, 1999-2004; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Newspaper articles, 2004-2010; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Published poems, 1997-2014; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Published poems and law journal article, 2007-2009, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Muckworks, 2009; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Drafts of poems, 1994, undated; Series 1 Subseries 2 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Writings by other authors, 1992-2010; Series 2
  Arranged in no particular order.
  This series contains poems, articles and essays written by various authors. The material dates from 1992-2010.
  - Poetry by other authors: Bedward's Fall by Sindey March, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Poetry by other authors: Curious Bodies by Yona Harvey, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Poetry by other authors: Rights of Passage by Kamau Brathwaite, undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Poetry by other authors: Something for My Sisters by Kenneth Carroll, 1992; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Poetry by other authors: Songs for Sarasvati by DJ Renegade, 1996; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poetry by other authors: Song Singing Songs by Delbert Tibbs, 1999; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Poetry by other authors, 1995-2004; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Poetry by other authors, 2005-2009; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Poetry by other authors, Undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Articles and Essays by other authors, 2007-2010, Undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Articles and Essays by other authors, Undated; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Articles and essays by other artists, Undated; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Research materials, 1978-2006; Series 3
  This series contains documents gathered by Brian Gilmore. These materials date from 1978-2006.
  - Research materials: historical, undated; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Research materials: home rule, undated; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Research materials: jazz, 2005-2006; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Research materials: malt liquor, 1998; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Research materials: May Miller, 1986-2002; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Research materials: musicians, 1994-2006; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Research materials: violence and poverty in Washington D.C., undated; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Research Materials, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Research Materials, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Research Materials, undated; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Notebook, scrapbook, 1978-1994; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Handwritten notes, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Publicity, 1986-2012; Series 4
  Arranged loosely chronologically.
  This series contains fliers, posters, handbills, press releases, and newspaper clippings related to the life of Brian Gilmore as a poet.
  - Reading events, 1986-2012; 2011-2012; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Fliers, handbills, programs and invitations, 1988-2008; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fliers, posters and handbills, undated; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Event fliers, 1990-2014; Series 4 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Press releases, reviews, 1997-2001; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1987-2006; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Publicity Materials, 1988-2010; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Publicity Materials, 2011; Series 4 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Personal files, 1977-2012; Series 5
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains legal documents, correspondence, photographs, and course work.
  - Brian Gilmore MTV Audition, 1994; Series 5 (Box 4, Videocassette 1)
  - Biographical materials, 1998-2014; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, awards, undated; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Contacts, undated; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1988-2008; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, undated; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1993-2010; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1993-2014; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Headshot, 2004 May; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 9, Cd 1)
  - Legal documents, 1989-2008; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters, undated; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newsletters, undated; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Personal files, 1995-2009; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, undated; Series 5 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Progressive Media Project Annual Reports, 2002-2006; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Screenwriting Class Files, 2007; Series 5 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sterling A. Brown honored at UMUM fete in Washington DC by James G. Spady, 1977; Series 5 (Box 7, Folder 2)